<document>

  <properties>
    <title>More than a Javascript/CSS compressor</title>
  </properties>
	
	<head>
		<style>
			h2{display:none}
			#firstPara{
				clear:right;
				margin-top:100px
			}
			#mainJawrLogo {
				border:0 !important;
				margin:auto 0 auto;
				float:left;
			}
			#jawrlinks {
				float:right;
				width:45%;
				text-align:right;
				margin-right:-20px;
			}
			#jawrlinks img {
				margin-bottom:10px;
			}
			#badges{
				float:right;
				clear:right;
			}
			#badges img  { border:0 !important;}
		</style>
	</head>
	
  <body>
	
    <section>
	
	<img src="./images/index/logo.png" style="border:0 !important" id="mainJawrLogo"  />
	
	<div id="jawrlinks">
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=8543">
			<img src="./images/index/download.png" style="border:0 !important" title="Download the latest version of Jawr"  /></a> 
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/tutorials/quickstart.html" >
			<img src="./images/index/get-started.png" style="border:0 !important" title="Go to the quickstart tutorial and start using Jawr" /></a> 		
	</div>
	<div id="badges">
		<!-- FURL -->
	<a href="http://www.furl.net/storeIt.jsp?t=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor&amp;u=https://jawr.dev.java.net" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/furl.png" alt="add to furl"/></a>  
	
	<!-- DEL.ICIO.US -->
	<a href="http://del.icio.us/post?v=4&amp;noui&amp;jump=close&amp;url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/delicious.png" alt="add to del.icio.us"/></a>  
	
	<!-- TECHNORATI -->
	<a href="http://technorati.com/faves?add=https://jawr.dev.java.net" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/technorati.png" alt="add to technorati"/></a>  
	
	<!-- BLINKLIST -->
	<a href="http://www.blinklist.com/index.php?Action=Blink/addblink.php&amp;Url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;Title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/blinklist.png" alt="add to blinklist"/></a>  
	
	<!-- DIGG -->
	<a href="http://digg.com/submit?phase=2&amp;url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/digg.png" alt="add to digg"/></a>  
	
	<!-- GOOGLE -->
	<a href="http://www.google.com/bookmarks/mark?op=edit&amp;output=popup&amp;bkmk=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/google.png" alt="add to google"/></a>  
	
	<!-- STUMBLEUPON -->
	<a href="http://www.stumbleupon.com/submit?url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/stumbleupon.png" alt="add to stumbleupon"/></a>  
	
	<!-- YAHOO -->
	<a href="http://myweb.yahoo.com/myresults/bookmarklet?t=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor&amp;u=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;ei=UTF" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/yahoo.png" alt="add to yahoo"/></a> 

	</div>
		
	<div id="firstPara">	
	
	
	
	<p>Jawr is a tunable packaging solution for Javascript and CSS which allows for rapid development of resources in separate module files. 
	Developers can work with a large set of split javascript files in development mode, then Jawr bundles all together into one or several files 
	in a configurable way. 
	<br/>By using a tag library, Jawr allows you to use the same, unchanged pages for development and production. 
	Jawr also minifies and compresses the files, resulting in reduced page load times. 
	<br/>Jawr is configured using a simple .properties descriptor, and aside of standard java web applications it can also be used with 
	<a href="https://facelets.dev.java.net/">Facelets</a> and <a href="http://grails.org/">Grails</a> applications.   
	</p>
	</div>
  	
  	<img src="./images/index/jawr.png" />
	<p>
	It is common knowledge that it is faster to serve one large file rather than two smaller ones, because of increased HTTP negotiation and the fact 
	that most browsers only keep two connections open to the same host at any given time. 
	Jawr will reduce the number of requests needed to load a page and the amount of data to transfer to clients, achieving drastic improvement of 
	loading times. With a simple configuration file, resources can be distributed in bundles to best suit the usage pattern for a site. 
	Files not added to bundles also benefit from minification and compression (if no bundles are declared, Jawr will work as an easy to configure
	resources compressor). 
	</p>	
	<p>
	A JSP tag library (Facelets also supported) is used to import the resources to pages. In development mode, the tags generate &lt;script&gt; and &lt;style&gt; links for each resource 
	mapped to a bundle.
	In production mode, the tags generate a single link pointing to the bundle file. Thus, there is no need to change code in pages when switching 
	from development to production mode. 
	</p>	
	<p>
	There is an increasing trend towards richer client interfaces with complex javascript implementations. Using Jawr will ease the development process 
	by allowing to distribute modules in separate files without worrying about how the application will be served to clients. 
	</p>	
	<p>
		The alternatives to using Jawr are: 
		<ul>
			<li>Developing all-in-one script files which conform to the deployment scheme. That is, cram all the modules into a few files. Version control becomes
			unmanageable and it is hard to find a component that needs change. As the project grows, the code becomes near to impossible to mantain. 
			</li>
			<li>Use a build script to join and compress the files, which forces developers to build and redeploy the whole application for testing  even the 
				slightest of changes in their code. 
				</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		Jawr offers the best of both worlds, by combining a powerful bundling-minifying-compressing scheme for optimal service in 
		production, with a rapid development mode for quick change-save-test cycles. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You can download the latest release of Jawr 
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=8543">here</a>. Also, check out the 
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/tutorials/quickstart.html">quick start tutorial</a> to see how easy it is to use Jawr in your project. 

	</p>
	
	
      <subsection name="Features">
		<ul>
			
			<li> <strong>Free and open source</strong>: Released under an Apache 2.0 license, Jawr can be used free of charge with or 
			without modifications, for both commercial and noncommercial purposes.</li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Easy to setup</strong>: All you need to start using Jawr is to declare a couple of servlets in you deployment descriptor, create a simple .properties configuration file, 
			and use the Jawr tag library to import css and javascript resources to your pages. A complete setup takes a matter of minutes and requires little or no modifications over time. </li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Lightweight</strong>: Bundling and compression is done once at server startup so there is no overhead to requests. Also, a cache component
			is available and enabled by default to serve resources directly from memory instead of from the filesystem.</li> 
			
			
			<li> <strong>Built-in minification and postprocessing</strong>: Jawr includes JSMin and the YUI compressor, both from Yahoo!. A custom minificator for 
			CSS is also included, although the YUI compressor can be used for CSS too. For each bundle, a customizable postprocessing chain is executed 
			during startup. Relative URLs in CSS files are rewritten by a postprocessor so they keep working with a different relative path. It is also 
			easy to create custom postprocessors to perform any modifications to your js and css files at deploy time. </li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Proxy-friendly gzip support</strong>: For each bundle there are two URLs that point to a gzipped and a regular version of the resource. Since the URLs 
			are be generated within a JSP, the request headers are analyzed to decide if the browser will support gzipping and the appropiate URL is written out. 
			With this system, caching proxies will not be a problem since it works around known Internet Explorer problems with the VARY header.</li> 
			
			
			<li> <strong>Caching enforcement</strong>: Jawr will try its best to force your clients to cache the resources. If a browser asks if a file changed, a 304 (not modified) 
			header is sent back with no content. On the other hand, with Jawr you will be 100% sure that new versions of your bundles are downloaded by all 
			clients. Every URL to your resources will include an automatically generated, content-based prefix that changes automatically whenever a 
			resurce is updated. Once you deploy a new version, the URL to the bundle will change as well so it will be impossible that a client uses an 
			older, cached version.</li> 
			
			
			<li> <strong>Flexible bundling scheme</strong>: Choose which files go into which bundle, and in which order. Choose wether you want a bundle minified or not. 
			Choose wether a bundle will be used only in development mode (for adding things such as console loggers). Create partially minified bundles. 
			Create bundles which are automatically added within an Internet Explorer conditional comment.  
			All with a very easy to use configuration system.</li> 
			
			
			<li> <strong>Global bundles</strong>: Some bundles such as libraries will be needed anywhere in your site where there is javascript code. Same goes for base CSS 
			stylesheets. With Jawr, these will be added to pages automatically so you don't need to repeat the same import statement everywhere.</li> 
			
			<li> <strong>JSF/Facelets support</strong>: If you are using JSF with Facelets as the view technology, you can still use Jawr using a specific tag library.</li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Grails plugin</strong>: Jawr can be used seamlessly in Grails applications, using a provided plugin that includes a GSP tag library.</li> 
		
			<li> <strong>DWR integration</strong>: You can use DWR and have Jawr handle the serving of the static and dynamic scripts DWR generates, with the 
					added feature of being able to bundle them together and with other scripts from your application. </li> 
					
			<li> <strong>Library friendly</strong>: Open source javascript libraries can be used seamlessly with Jawr. Most of these are modular or have plugins: add the modules or 
			plugins you need and bundle all together. And, even if you minify them (thus eliminating comments), you can still keep the mandatory licenses in
			the bundle. The <a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/tutorials/quickstart.html">libraries tutorial</a> will show you how to integrate popular js libraries such 
			as Protoype, JQuery or YUI. </li>
		</ul>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Requirements">
      	<p>
      		You can use Jawr with any compliant Java Servlet 2.3 or higher container implementation (i.e. Tomcat, Jetty, BEA Weblogic etc.), as long as the 
			virtual machine it runs on is 1.4 or higher. Jawr uses Apache log4j for logging messages, so it is a required library. There are no other requirements, 
			although if your JVM version is 1.4, you can improve performance by using the backport-util-concurrent library, which can be found at: 
			<a href="http://backport-jsr166.sourceforge.net/">http://backport-jsr166.sourceforge.net</a>. However, this is completely optional and Jawr will work 
			just fine if you choose not to use it.  
      	</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Announcements">
      <ul>
      	<li> <strong>6/2/2008</strong>: Version 2.2 released:<br/> <strong>DWR integration</strong>: DWR users can now leverage the new integration with Jawr, 
      	which allows bundling all DWR resources along with other static scripts. <br/>
      	<strong>Mapping of classpath resources: </strong> bundles can now map to  resources (javascript and CSS) which are available in the classpath. 
      	<br/>				      	
				Also, several bugs were fixed: 
				<ul><li> bug in i18n message generation: was failing when a dollar sign was found in a message. </li>
				
				<li> bug for i18n messages: in debug mode, would get 404s if the mapping was not set to attend *.js requests. </li>
				
				<li> bug in CSS link rewriter, which failed when Jawr mapping had several subdomains. </li>
				
				<li> Decreased logging verbosity of the ConcurrentCollectionsFactory. </li></ul>
      	</li>

      	<li> <strong>5/19/2008</strong>: Version 2.1 released: <strong>i18n messages mapping from java ResourceBundles to javascript:</strong> 
      	your internationalized messages that you keep in properties files can be easily converted into a script that allows for easy access to 
      	every message and supports variable substitution. According tho the user's locale, the script generated will correspond to his language.   
      	<br/>Other than that, mostly internal changes and bugfixes. The internal changes include a new system to 
      	map to Generators. These are java components which generate javascript/CSS, or read it from a different place than the usual WAR directories.
      	This opens interesting possibilities for the near future. 
      	</li>
      	<li> <strong>4/5/2008</strong>: Version 2.0 released: new automatic prefixing system, conditional comments support, grails and facelets 
      	plugins, YUI compressor... Check the <a href="./docs/changes_20.html" >what's new in 2.0 page</a> for a description of all the new features and fixes.    
      	</li>
      	<li> <strong>2/28/2008</strong>: Version 1.4 released. Many issues resolved: 
			<ul>
				<li> #5: It is now possible to add a custom class to handle the loading of properties configuration. Check the <a href="/docs/servlet.html">servlet documentation</a> for details. 
					</li>
				<li> #7: Added <em>useRandomParam</em> attribute to the taglibs, so that in development mode you can have Jawr not use random parameters in URLs. 
				</li>
				<li> #8: Fixed an invalid log message. 
				</li>
				<li> #9: Bug in initialization process for CSS postprocessors. 
				</li>
				<li> #10: <strong>(cool!)</strong> You can now use custom made postprocessors in Jawr. Check the <a href="/docs/postprocessors.html">postprocessors documentation</a> for details. 
				</li>
				<li> #11: Jawr can now be configured to use a different prefix other than the context path for generated URLs. 
				</li>
				<li> #13: Fixed a Classloader issue that arises when Jawr is on a different classloader than that of the web application using it. 
				</li>
				</ul>
				Also, Jawr can now be configured to reload itself when the configuration file changes, without having to restart the server. Set the 
				<em>jawr.config.reload.interval</em> param to a value for an interval in seconds and you are ready to go. 
		</li>
		
		<li> <strong>2/13/2008</strong>: Version 1.3 released. Fixes a major bug in the CSS URL rewriter (issue #2). Many log statements are changed from info to debug (issue 
			#4). Some refactoring to abstract base tag library, to allow for easier custom implementations of tag renderers not depending on JSP technology. 
		</li>
		
		<li> <strong>2/13/2008</strong>: New developer joins the project: Suresh Thalluri volunteered to join the project and will be helping improve Jawr. Welcome aboard!
		</li>
		
		<li> <strong>2/1/2008</strong>: Version 1.2 released. The project packages are all renamed to remove all references to java (i.e. packages named net.java.jawr are 
			now simply net.jawr). This is due to the standard naming scheme not being valid for java.net because of copyright issues. Therefore the 
			servlet and other components have a new name, so if you were already using jawr you will need to change any references. Hopefully there will be no 
			more changes to the packaging scheme. Also, the servlet API version dependency was set to 2.3 in the POM (was 2.5 by mistake). 
		</li>
		
		<li> <strong>1/31/2008</strong>: Version 1.1 released, fixes a major problem with the taglib descriptor and adds the option to use @startup for generating 
				bundle prefixes upon deployment. 
		</li>
		
      </ul>
      </subsection>
      

    </section>
  </body>

</document>