<document>

  <properties>
    <title>More than a Javascript/CSS compressor</title>
  </properties>
	
	<head>
		<style>
			h2{display:none}
			#firstPara{
				clear:right;
				margin-top:100px
			}
			#mainJawrLogo {
				border:0 !important;
				margin:auto 0 auto;
				float:left;
			}
			#jawrlinks {
				float:right;
				width:45%;
				text-align:right;
				margin-right:-20px;
			}
			#jawrlinks img {
				margin-bottom:10px;
			}
			#badges{
				float:right;
				clear:right;
			}
			#badges img  { border:0 !important;}
		</style>
	</head>
	
  <body>
	
    <section>
	<img src="./images/index/logo.png" style="border-width:0 !important" id="mainJawrLogo"  />
	
	<div id="jawrlinks">
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=8543">
			<img src="./images/index/download.png" style="border-width:0 !important" title="Download the latest version of Jawr"  /></a> 
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/tutorials/quickstart.html" >
			<img src="./images/index/get-started.png" style="border-width:0 !important" title="Go to the quickstart tutorial and start using Jawr" /></a> 		
	</div>
	<div id="badges">
		<!-- FURL -->
	<a href="http://www.furl.net/storeIt.jsp?t=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor&amp;u=https://jawr.dev.java.net" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/furl.png" alt="add to furl"/></a>  
	
	<!-- DEL.ICIO.US -->
	<a href="http://del.icio.us/post?v=4&amp;noui&amp;jump=close&amp;url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/delicious.png" alt="add to del.icio.us"/></a>  
	
	<!-- TECHNORATI -->
	<a href="http://technorati.com/faves?add=https://jawr.dev.java.net" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/technorati.png" alt="add to technorati"/></a>  
	
	<!-- BLINKLIST -->
	<a href="http://www.blinklist.com/index.php?Action=Blink/addblink.php&amp;Url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;Title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/blinklist.png" alt="add to blinklist"/></a>  
	
	<!-- DIGG -->
	<a href="http://digg.com/submit?phase=2&amp;url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/digg.png" alt="add to digg"/></a>  
	
	<!-- GOOGLE -->
	<a href="http://www.google.com/bookmarks/mark?op=edit&amp;output=popup&amp;bkmk=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/google.png" alt="add to google"/></a>  
	
	<!-- STUMBLEUPON -->
	<a href="http://www.stumbleupon.com/submit?url=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;title=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/stumbleupon.png" alt="add to stumbleupon"/></a>  
	
	<!-- YAHOO -->
	<a href="http://myweb.yahoo.com/myresults/bookmarklet?t=JAWR%20-%20More%20than%20a%20javascript/css%20compressor&amp;u=https://jawr.dev.java.net&amp;ei=UTF" target="_blank"><img border="0" src="/images/badges/yahoo.png" alt="add to yahoo"/></a> 

	</div>
		
	<div id="firstPara">	
	
	
	
	<p>Jawr is a tunable packaging solution for Javascript and CSS which allows for rapid development of resources in separate module files. 
	Developers can work with a large set of split javascript files in development mode, then Jawr bundles all together into one or several files 
	in a configurable way. 
	<br/>By using a tag library, Jawr allows you to use the same, unchanged pages for development and production. 
	Jawr also minifies and compresses the files, resulting in reduced page load times. 
	<br/>Jawr is configured using a simple .properties descriptor, and aside of standard java web applications it can also be used with 
	<a href="https://facelets.dev.java.net/">Facelets</a> and <a href="http://grails.org/">Grails</a> applications.   
	</p>
	</div>
  	
  	<img src="./images/index/jawr.png" />
	<p>
	It is common knowledge that it is faster to serve one large file rather than two smaller ones, because of increased HTTP negotiation and the fact 
	that most browsers only keep two connections open to the same host at any given time. 
	Jawr will reduce the number of requests needed to load a page and the amount of data to transfer to clients, achieving drastic improvement of 
	loading times. With a simple configuration file, resources can be distributed in bundles to best suit the usage pattern for a site. 
	Files not added to bundles also benefit from minification and compression (if no bundles are declared, Jawr will work as an easy to configure
	resources compressor). 
	</p>	
	<p>
	A JSP tag library (Facelets also supported) is used to import the resources to pages. In development mode, the tags generate &lt;script&gt; and &lt;style&gt; links for each resource 
	mapped to a bundle.
	In production mode, the tags generate a single link pointing to the bundle file. Thus, there is no need to change code in pages when switching 
	from development to production mode. 
	</p>	
	<p>
	There is an increasing trend towards richer client interfaces with complex javascript implementations. Using Jawr will ease the development process 
	by allowing to distribute modules in separate files without worrying about how the application will be served to clients. 
	</p>	
	<p>
		The alternatives to using Jawr are: 
		<ul>
			<li>Developing all-in-one script files which conform to the deployment scheme. That is, cram all the modules into a few files. Version control becomes
			unmanageable and it is hard to find a component that needs change. As the project grows, the code becomes near to impossible to mantain. 
			</li>
			<li>Use a build script to join and compress the files, which forces developers to build and redeploy the whole application for testing  even the 
				slightest of changes in their code. 
				</li>
		</ul>
	</p>
	<p>
		Jawr offers the best of both worlds, by combining a powerful bundling-minifying-compressing scheme for optimal service in 
		production, with a rapid development mode for quick change-save-test cycles. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You can download the latest release of Jawr 
		<a href="https://jawr.dev.java.net/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=8543">here</a>. Also, check out the 
		<a href="./tutorials/quickstart.html">quick start tutorial</a> to see how easy it is to use Jawr in your project. 
		<br/>And don't forget to check the <a href="./tutorials/faq_howto.html">FAQ - Howto page</a> for tips and troubleshooting. 
	</p>
	
	
      <subsection name="Features">
		<ul>
			
			<li> <strong>Free and open source</strong>: Released under an Apache 2.0 license, Jawr can be used free of charge with or 
			without modifications, for both commercial and noncommercial purposes.</li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Easy to setup</strong>: All you need to start using Jawr is to declare a couple of servlets in you deployment descriptor, create a simple .properties configuration file, 
			and use the Jawr tag library to import css and javascript resources to your pages. A complete setup takes a matter of minutes and requires little or no modifications over time. </li> 
			
			<li> <strong>Lightweight</strong>: Bundling and compression is done once at server startup so there is no overhead to requests. Also, a cache component
			is available and enabled by default to serve resources directly from memory instead of from the filesystem.</li> 
			
			
			<li> <strong>Built-in minification and postprocessing</strong>: Jawr includes JSMin and the YUI compressor, both from Yahoo!. A custom minificator for 
			CSS is also included, although the YUI compressor can be used for CSS too. For each bundle, a customizable postprocessing chain is executed 
			during startup. Relative URLs in CSS files are rewritten by a postprocessor so they keep working with a different relative path. It is also 
			easy to create custom postprocessors to perform any modifications to your js and css files at deploy time. 
			 <a href="./docs/postprocessors.html" > Learn more</a>. 
			</li> 
			
			<li><strong>Third party frameworks integration</strong>: Jawr can be used with 
				<a href="./integration/dwr.html">DWR</a>, 
				<a href="./integration/spring.html">Spring</a>, JSF, 
				<a href="./integration/facelets.html">Facelets</a>, 
				<a href="./integration/validator.html">Commons Validator (with Struts)</a>, 
				 and <a href="./integration/grails.html">Grails.</a>  
				 It can also be easily plugged <a href="./integration/augmenter.html">into your own infrastructure. </a> 
			</li>			
		</ul>
		<p>There are many more features, check the <a href="./features.html">features list page</a> for a full listing. </p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Requirements">
      	<p>
      		You can use Jawr with any compliant Java Servlet 2.3 or higher container implementation (i.e. Tomcat, Jetty, BEA Weblogic etc.), as long as the 
			virtual machine it runs on is 1.4 or higher. Jawr uses Apache log4j for logging messages, so it is a required library. There are no other requirements, 
			although if your JVM version is 1.4, you can improve performance by using the backport-util-concurrent library, which can be found at: 
			<a href="http://backport-jsr166.sourceforge.net/">http://backport-jsr166.sourceforge.net</a>. However, this is completely optional and Jawr will work 
			just fine if you choose not to use it.  
      	</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Announcements">
      <p>Here are the latest announcements regarding Jawr. You can find older version announcements with all the features that have been 
      added over time at the <a href="./changes.html">change log.</a> </p>
      <ul>
      	<li> <strong>11/23/2008</strong>: Version 2.6 released:<br/> 
      		<strong>New features/ fixed issues: </strong>
      		 <ul><li> <strong>Spring MVC support added. </strong> Jawr now provides a Spring MVC Controller so it can be fully configured 
      		 through Spring's configuration mechanism. See <a href="./integration/spring.html" >the manual page</a> for details. </li>
      		 <li>The way LINK tags are rendered can now be configured. Specifically, depending on the content type you choose for your 
      		 pages, you may need the link tags to be closed differently, or even not closed at all. By default, tags will be closed as 
      		 usual (i.e. with '/&gt;'). But adding a new parameter to the properties configuration will make this behavior change. 
      		 Check the <a href="./docs/taglibs.html" > taglib documentation</a> and look for 'jawr.csslinks.flavor' for details.  </li>
      		 <li>A new generator has been added. Now CSS resources can be retrieved from the classpath by using the 
      		 <strong>jar_css</strong> prefix. </li>
      		 <li>[Issue #46] The jawr[css|js].bundle.names property is now augmentable when using ConfigPropertiesAugmenter, 
      		 as it should have from the start. </li>      		 
      		 <li>[Unregistered Issue] Jawr does not close the outputstream nor the output writers handed by the servlet container anymore, 
      		 since that's an illegal operation, as was pointed out by user Lance. </li>      		
			</ul>
      	</li>   
      	<li> <strong>11/9/2008</strong>: Version 2.5.1 released:<br/> 
      		<strong>New features/ fixed issues: </strong>
      		 <ul><li>[Grails, issue #26] Switched from using controllers to using a servlet: This has several advantages: it is faster, there is no 
      		 need to fiddle with the grails.mime.file.extensions property, and no controller mappings need to be added. So if you are upgrading, you 
      		 need to remove the controller mappings, reset the grails.mime.file.extensions property and then follow URL mapping instructions at the 
      		 <a href="./integration/grails.html" >plugin instructions page</a>. </li>
      		 <li>[Grails, issue #32] New grails-only implementation of the i18n messages generator that solves all previous issues. It is no longer 
      		 needed to copy properties files when deploying/running in war mode, and the previous message character encoding issues should 
      		 be gone for good. </li>
      		 <li>[Issue #44] Added code to respond with 304 to requests having the If-None-Match header. </li>      		 
      		 <li>Link tags are now ended with '/&gt;' as opposed to &lt;/link&gt;to improve validability. While in a perfect word 
      		there should be no closing tag at all in non-xhtml documents, this seems to be the best compromise.</li>  
      		 <li>Fixed improper exception handling at some points where stack data was being spoiled. </li>
			</ul>
      	</li>   
      	<li> <strong>10/7/2008</strong>: Version 2.5 released:<br/> 
      		<strong>New features: </strong>
      		 <ul><li>CDN support: Jawr can be used with a CDN by setting the parameter to an absolute URL. </li>
      		 <li><a href="./docs/generators.html" >Generators API</a>: you can now write components that dynamically generate scripts or 
      		 CSS during the application startup. </li>
      		 <li>Ability to read config the file from the filesystem: instead of reading only from the classpath, the config properties file 
      		 can now be read from the filesystem. To do it the config parameter must be prefixed with file:, followed by the absolute file path. </li>      		 
      		 <li><a href="./integration/augmenter.html" >Multiple configuration sources</a> can be used when integrating Jawr with other frameworks.</li>
      		 </ul>
      		<strong>Fixed issues:</strong>
      		<ul><li>#31:media="print" ignored when useRandomParam="false" </li>
      		 <li>#29:Contextpath override does not work with absolute URLs (see CDN support above)</li>
      		 <li>#19:PropsFilePropertiesSource.configChanged() doesn't work on Tomcat (now properties can be read from the filesystem)</li>
      		 <li>Also, a new version of the DWR 3 has been published, fixing the latest incompatibilities. </li></ul>
      	</li>   
      </ul>
      </subsection>
      

    </section>
  </body>

</document>
